{
  "reference_number": "12139",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "By 2050 we shall still be partially reliant on non-renewable resources, not only because of the difficulty of adequately expanding\n electricity generation, but also the disruptive consequences of scaling down or eliminating whole industries. Hence a valiant effort to\n reduce dependence on fossil fuels but with an eye to internal problems and overseas competitors."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Clearly there will be a need to use some emission reductions from overseas."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I remain sceptical about the consequences and extent of AGW.. The 'prophets of doom' offer an apocalyptic vision of the future, as\n visionaries have through the ages. All of them have been wrong. They start from an uncertain base and extrapolate into the distant\n\n future. In spite of the claims of impending doom, Change should be gradual and well signalled."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "It is obviously sensible to be able to modify targets in the light of events. No government should be tied to such distant decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "For the same reason. An incoming government may well have to act in the face of changing circumstances. We have seen how a\n\nworld view has changed in the last few months, and government must be given the freedom to respond"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It is overarching and ambitious, and largely produced by non-scientists with an unhealthy dose of social context. The considerations\nneed much more careful analysis and projection, and more informed public debate."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In a broad sense a 'transparent' government should be quite clear about its plans. What has been produced so far is little better than\na 'chicken little' approach."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Clarity of purpose and transparency. Government will need to remember that purity of purpose may require some hard economic and\n\nsocial considerations, and changing circumstances may bring soem harsh reality."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is self-fulfilling prophecy. Who can say what expertise is desirable? All through this document is the confusion between climate\nand weather. A few warm or wet years do not constitute impending disaster. Prudence should be the watchword"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "What else can it do?"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The entire economy of the country could be seriously impacted by moves to include methane in the Zero Emissions Bill.\n\nConsideration of this should be postponed while new solutions are investigated, e.g. selective breeding or development of vaccines."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Festina lente - make haste slowly and deliberately. The hysteria raised by geographers desperate to sup at the trough has been too\nstrident, and my impression is that the public is largely indifferent. The very much minority 'green component of the government\n\nappears to be punishing its own base by wanting to compel the public ot ride buses and use bicycles. They should be compelled to\nlive in Dunedin and collect their groceries in a storm"
    }
  ]
}
